Finding Aid for Karl Detzer papers, 1916-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Karl Detzer papers 1916-1981
Detzer, Karl, 1891-
851111 Aa 2
Leland, Michigan, journalist and author. Papers relating to his work as writer and editor for Reader's Digest; scripts and other papers concerning his activities as scriptwriter for radio, television, and motion picture production; copies of magazine articles; and material concerning the role of the United States in Mexican border troubles prior to World War I; also photographs.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Karl Detzer (donor no. 4368 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Karl Detzer was born September 4, 1891 in Fort Wayne, Indiana. A journalist and free-lance writer, Detzer began his career working for a Fort Wayne newspaper as a reporter and photographer. Following service in World War I, he came to Chicago where wrote advertising copy. He would leave this to write full-time on his own, writing for various pulp magazines, submitting screenplays to Hollywood studios, eventually working as a roving editor for Reader's Digest. He died April 28, 1987 in Leland, Michigan, where some years earlier he had made his home.
The collections includes biographical and personal materials, correspondence, clippings, articles, motion picture and radio scripts, photographs, and copies of his writings from various magazines.
Subjects:
Authors, American--Michigan.; Journalists--Michigan--Leland.; Leland (Mich.); Mexico--Frontier troubles--1910-; Motion picture industry--United States.; Radio broadcasting--United States.; The Reader's Digest.; Television broadcasting--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Beaver Island (Mich.); Cemeteries--Michigan.; Ferries.; Frankfort (Mich.); Garden Island (Charlevoix County, Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan.; Milliken, John.; Milliken, William G., 1922-; Milliken family.; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
Genre Terms:
Christmas cards.; Photographs.
- Biographical and personal material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1916 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942 (Box 1)
  - 1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1945 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1945 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1945 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978 (Box 1)
  - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
- Clippings
  - circa 1916-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1981 (Box 1)
  - Book reviews, etc. undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Chicago Tribune articles, May 23-July 11, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Reviews of "Contrabando," 1934 (Box 1)
  - "Wanderings" articles in Leelanau Enterprise 1948-1957 (Box 1)
  - re. Great Lakes shipping (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Detzer articles (Box 1)
- Articles, movie productions, radio programs
  - "Car 99"
    - Movie script 1935 (Box 2)
    - Press clippings, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 2)
  - "Myself When Young" (Box 2)
  - "'Crime-Stop' Stops Crime" (Box 2)
  - "Riot" Movie script 1953 (Box 2)
  - "Lincoln's Sandburg" Article and research material (Box 2)
  - "Trouble on the Great Lakes" Article and research material (Box 2)
  - "State Trooper" (radio program) Scripts and correspondence 1938 (Box 2)
  - "Tillie Scrubbed On" (movie) Correspondence and contract 1947 (Box 2)
  - Booklet, "Song of War" by Karl Detzer Jr. (Box 2)
  - "The Professors to the Rescue," 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - "Our Great Big Highway Bungle," 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 2)
- Miscellanea
  - Walter Wanger article, etc. (Box 2)
  - Beaver Island notes (Box 2)
  - Sleeping Bear Dunes (Box 2)
  - Leland Stowe poetry (Box 2)
  - Publishing contracts,agreements,etc. 1938-1944 (Box 2)
  - Contracts, royalty statements,etc. 1957-1960 (Box 2)
  - Copies of magazine articles (Box 3)
    (arranged by magazine title; partial index included with the articles)
  - Photographs, 6 envelopes
    - Informal photos; award presentations (Box 3)
    - William Milliken family (Box 3)
    - John G. Milliken family (Box 3)
    - Murray D. Van Wagoner (Box 3)
    - Translators' meeting, Stuttgart February 9, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)